Benjamin S. Loeb Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Benjamin S. Loeb Papers 1945-1999 (bulk 1961-1971)
MSS84718
Loeb, Benjamin S., 1914-
6,000 items
17 containers plus 1 classified
6.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Economist, author, and government official. Research files containing journal excerpts, correspondence, memoranda, cables, reports, minutes, interview transcripts, writings, speeches, newspaper clippings, and printed matter compiled by Loeb concerning Glenn Theodore Seaborg's chairmanship of the Atomic Energy Commission from 1961 to 1971. Loeb assisted Seaborg in writing several books on his chairmanship which feature Seaborg's efforts to promote arms control and peaceful uses of nuclear power.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bundy, McGeorge--Correspondence.; Bundy, McGeorge--Interviews.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986--Correspondence.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986--Interviews.; Loeb, Benjamin S., 1914-; Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, 1912-; Shapiro, Zalman M. (Zalmon Mordecai), 1920-; Sorensen, Theodore C.--Correspondence.; Sorensen, Theodore C.--Interviews.
Organizations
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.
Subjects
Arms control.; Espionage, Israeli--United States.; Nuclear energy--Government policy--United States.; Political crimes and offenses--Investigation--United States.; Security, International.; Uranium enrichment.
Occupations
Authors.; Economists.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of Benjamin S. Loeb, economist, author, and government official, were given to the Library of Congress by Loeb in 2000.
Transfers
Audio cassette recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
The Loeb Papers complement the Glenn Theodore Seaborg Papers also located in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress. The General Correspondence and Writings series in the Seaborg Papers contain large quantities of correspondence between Seaborg and Loeb concerning their collaborative efforts.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Benjamin S. Loeb are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified items.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1914, Mar. 5 Born, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1935 A.B., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1939 1942 Analyst, Security and Exchange Commission
1942 1945 Economist and statistician, War Production Board
1945 1948 Management research, Saks and Co., New York, N.Y.
1948 M.B.A., New York University, New York, N.Y.
1948 1951 Research economist, National Security Resources Board
1951 1953 Statistician, Defense Electric Power Administration
1953 1955 Instructor in management and retailing, Columbia University and City College of New York, New York, N.Y.
1955 1960 Writer, Atomic Energy Commission
1958 Ph.D., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1960 1962 Editorial specialist on nuclear power, Division of Public Information, International Atomic Energy Commission
1964 Published with John Lawrence and Bernard Manowitz Radioisotopes and Radiation (New York: McGraw-Hill Book Co. 131 pp.)
1970 1971 Conducted special research and writing projects for Glenn Theodore Seaborg, chairman, Atomic Energy Commission
1971 1974 Speech writer, Atomic Energy Commission
1974 1976 Editor, Nuclear Regulatory Commission
1977 Writer and consultant
1981 Assisted Glenn Theodore Seaborg in writing Kennedy, Khrushchev and the Test Ban (Berkeley, Calif.: University of California Press. 320 pp.)
1987 Assisted Glenn Theodore Seaborg in writing Stemming the Tide: Arms Control in the Johnson Years (Lexington, Mass.: Lexington Books. 495 pp.)
1995 Assisted Glenn Theodore Seaborg in writing The Atomic Energy Commission under Nixon: Adjusting to Troubled Times (New York: St. Martin's Press. 268 pp.)
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Benjamin S. Loeb (1914- ) span the years 1945-1999, with the bulk of the material dating from 1961 to 1971. The papers concern Loeb's collaboration with Glenn Theodore Seaborg on several books concerning Seaborg's chairmanship of the Atomic Energy Commission from 1961 to 1971. The books, each of which focuses on a presidential administration, explore Seaborg's efforts to promote arms control and peaceful uses of nuclear power. The collection consists of research files containing excerpts from Seaborg's journal, correspondence, memoranda, cables, reports, minutes, interview transcripts, writings, speeches, newspaper clippings, and printed matter. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
A large portion of Loeb's research files consists of material culled from the Seaborg Papers located in this division. Loeb relied heavily on Seaborg's journal which contains diary-like entries supplemented by copies of correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, and printed matter. Loeb's files provide topical access to the chronologically-arranged journal on issues such as arms control and test ban treaties, the environment, fast breeder reactors, multilateral force, peaceful nuclear explosions, plowshare programs, and uranium enrichment. Many of the photocopied documents contain Loeb's annotations.
Loeb augmented his use of Seaborg's papers with research at the John F. Kennedy Library in Cambridge, Massachusetts, the Lyndon B. Johnson Library in Austin, Texas, and the National Archives and Records Administration in Washington, D.C. Files relating to the Limited Test Ban Treaty of 1963 include copies of State Department cables secured by Loeb through Freedom of Information Act requests. Also included in the collection are Loeb's correspondence and interviews with prominent former government officials including McGeorge Bundy, W. Averell Harriman, and Theodore C. Sorensen.
Featured in the collection is Loeb's investigation into allegations that Zalman Shapiro, president of the Nuclear Materials and Equipment Corporation of Pennsylvania, provided Israeli associates with nuclear secrets and enriched uranium in the 1960s. Included are copies of Federal Bureau of Investigation memoranda and reports attained by Loeb through the Freedom of Information Act.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by name of person, organization, or topic.
Container List
- Anti-ballistic missile system, 1969, 1986 (Box 1)
- Arms control
  - Atomic Energy Commission histories, 1968-1971, (2 folders)
  - Executive branch organizational issues, 1969-1970
  - Franck, James, report and other early debates, 1945-1964, 1978-1983, undated
  - General file, 1966-1971, undated
- Atomic Energy Commission, 1966-1971, undated
- Australia, Cape Keraudren plowshare project, 1969, undated
- Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty
  - Arguments in favor of
    - Ban, 1972-1992, undated, (2 folders)
    - Testing, 1982-1988, undated (Box 2)
  - Center for Defense Information, 1984
  - Dewitt, Hugh, 1962, 1974-1985, undated
  - History, 1970, 1980-1987, undated
  - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, journal excerpts, 1969-1971, undated
- Bundy, McGeorge, 1964-1986, undated
- Cousins, Norman, 1980
- Cuban missile crisis, 1962, 1973-1977
- Education and student unrest, 1969-1971, 1989, undated
- Enola Gay exhibit, Air and Space Museum, Washington, D.C., 1990-1995
- Environment
  - Jurisdictional responsibility, 1969-1973, undated
  - Miscellany, 1969-1970, 1991, undated
  - Northern States Power Co. v. Minnesota Pollution Control Agency, 1969-1970
  - Opposition to nuclear energy, 1969-1971, 1989, undated
  - Radioactive pollution from nuclear power plants, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Radioactive waste, 1969-1971
- Euratom, 1964-1969, 1997, undated
- Fast breeder reactors, 1969-1972, undated, (2 folders)
- Federal budget, 1969-1971, undated
- Gilpatric, Roswell L., 1964-1965, 1984-1985, undated
- Goffman, John, and Arthur Tamplin, 1969-1971, 1982-1989, undated
- Hanford Atomic Reactor, Richland, Wash., 1969-1970
- Harriman, W. Averell
  - Interviews, 1980-1981, undated
  - Miscellany, 1963-1964, 1973, 1983, undated (Box 4)
- Herken, Gregg, 1986
- International Atom Program, 1969-1984
- International Atomic Energy Agency, 1961-1970, 1985-1997
- John F. Kennedy Library, Cambridge, Mass., research notes and photocopies, 1962-1964, 1980, undated
- Johnson, Lyndon B.
  - Cabinet meetings, 1964-1967, undated
  - Conduct in office, 1969-1971, undated
  - Miscellany, 1963-1973, undated
  - Oral history citations, 1965-1971
  - Personal traits, 1970-1973, undated
  - Relationship with Glenn Theodore Seaborg, 1963-1966
  - Secrecy, undated
  - Summit meeting with Alexei Kosygin, Glassboro, N.J., 1967, 1986
  - Vietnam War, 1964-1984, undated See also Container 16, same heading
- Limited Test Ban Treaty
  - Amendments, 1985-1992
  - Cables, copies received through Freedom of Information Act requests, 1963, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Kennedy, John F., recorded telephone conversations, 1963, 1988
  - Public reaction, 1989-1990
- Low-threshold nuclear test ban, 1981-1987
- Merchant ships, undated
- Moyers, Bill, 1969-1972, undated
- Multilateral force, 1962-1966, undated See also Classified, (2 folders)
- National energy situation, 1970-1971, undated
- Netherlands, nuclear submarine program, 1969-1970
- Nixon, Richard M., 1969-1971, 1989
- Non-Proliferation Treaty
  - General file
    - 1964-1968, (2 folders)
    - 1969-1992, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Review conferences, Geneva, Switzerland, 1968-1985
  - Safeguards, 1964-1968, 1985, undated, (2 folders)
  - United States as supplier of nuclear fuel, 1963-1967
- Nuclear free zones, 1967-1968, 1983, undated
- Nuclear Materials and Equipment Corp.
  - Atomic Energy Agency interviews and memoranda, 1966-1971, 1991-1993
  - Chronology, undated
  - Coverup investigation, 1976-1979, undated
  - Decommissioning enriched uranium operations, 1981-1983, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Explanation of uranium losses, 1976-1979
  - “Fact” file concerning allegations, 1965-1969, 1976-1979, undated
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation
    - Interviews, 1978-1979
    - Investigations, 1969-1978
    - Progress of investigations and findings, 1966-1981, undated
  - Government Accounting Office report, 1978-1979, 1993
  - Health allegations, 1980
  - Keller, Charles A., notes, 1962-1969, 1978-1979
  - Loading dock incidents, 1968, 1980, undated
  - Media coverage, 1969-1979, 1991, undated
  - Miscellany, 1966, 1991, undated
  - Physical security standards, 1966, 1974-1980
  - Public opinion, 1979
  - Reports, 1966, 1976-1979, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, journal excerpts, 1969-1971
  - Secrecy, 1980
  - Shapiro, Zalman, investigation and surveillance, 1966-1977, undated
  - Sources, undated
  - United States Congress, 1969, 1978
- Nuclear power and nuclear power facilities, 1969-1997, undated
- Peaceful nuclear explosions and plowshare programs
  - 1963-1967, (3 folders)
  - 1968-1990, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
- President's Advisory Council on Executive Organization, 1969-1973, undated
- Production
  - Buildup, 1958-1964, 1980-1981
  - Cutback
    - 1961-1969 See also Classified, (4 folders)
    - 1970-1980, undated (Box 10)
  - Economic impact and utility contracts, 1963-1965, undated
- Project Rulison, gas stimulation project, Colo., 1969-1970, undated
- Proliferation, 1963-1986, undated
- Regulatory reform, 1969-1983, undated
- Risks, 1970, 1987-1989, undated
- Rostow, W. W., 1971, 1983, undated
- Rusk, Dean, 1965, 1986, undated
- Safety, 1969-1971, 1989-1991
- Science, 1969-1971
- Seabed Arms Control Treaty, 1962-1970, undated
- Seaborg, Glenn Theodore (Box 11)
  - Journal excerpts For additional material see Container 2, Container 8, and Container 15, same heading
    - 1961, (4 folders)
    - 1962
      - Jan.- June, (3 folders)
      - July-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1963, (4 folders)
  - Meet the Press appearance, 1971 (Box 13)
  - Notes from conversations, 1971
  - Obituaries and memorial service program, 1999
  - Professional anecdotes, 1966-1971, 1985, (2 folders)
  - Travel abroad
    - Africa, 1970
    - Belgium, Netherlands, and Luxembourg, 1997, undated For additional material see Container 5, Netherlands
    - France, 1997
    - Germany, 1966-1967, 1975, 1997, undated
    - India, 1964-1983, 1997, undated
    - Italy, 1997
    - Japan, 1970, 1994-1997
    - Latin America, 1967
    - Miscellany, 1969-1971, undated
    - Sweden, 1997, undated
    - United Kingdom, 1963-1971, 1997, undated See also Classified, (2 folders)
- Secrecy and classification issues, 1985-1997, undated (Box 14)
- Sorenson, Theodore C., 1981
- Soviet Union, 1964-1991, undated, (2 folders)
- Space, 1969-1970
- Stassen, Harold Edward, 1963, 1983
- Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT), 1968-1971, 1986, undated
- Tamplin, Arthur See Container 3, Goffman, John
- Testing and test bans
  - Background, 1961-1983, undated
  - By presidential administration
    - Bush, George, 1989-1991, undated
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1980-1982
    - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1964-1968, undated, (2 folders)
    - Reagan, Ronald, 1981-1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Chronology, undated
  - Debate over testing, 1992
  - Nuclear testing, circa 1968-1971, 1986-1988, (2 folders)
  - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, journal excerpts, 1962-1971 See also Classified, (4 folders)
- Testing and test bans (Box 16)
  - Verification, 1970, 1982-1990
- Uranium
  - Enrichment, 1969-1989, undated, (4 folders)
  - Mining, 1969-1971
- Vietnam War, 1965-1983, undated See also Container 4, same heading
- Views of non-nuclear weapon states, 1967-1968, undated
- Wiesner, Jerome B., 1980
- Writings and speeches by
  - Loeb, 1988-1995
  - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, 1969-1971, 1982-1996, undated, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, and Loeb
    - The Atomic Energy Commission under Nixon
      - Material for epilogue, 1969-1992, undated
      - Reviews and reactions, 1993-1995
    - Kennedy, Khrushchev and the Test Ban, correspondence
      - Between Glenn Theodore Seaborg and Loeb, 1972-1980, undated
      - General, 1980-1983, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1985, 1993, undated
    - “My Three Presidents,” 1993, undated, (2 folders)
    - “Nuclear Diplomacy during the Cold War,” 1997-1998, undated For additional material see Container 13, Travel abroad
- Classified (Box CL 1)
  - Multilateral force, 1963 (Container 5)
  - Production
    - Cutback, 1965 (Container 9)
  - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore
    - Travel abroad
      - United Kingdom, 1963 (Container 13)
  - Testing and test bans
    - Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, journal excerpts, 1963 (Container 15)